<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crane Co.</ENAMEX> said it holds an 8.9% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Milton Roy Corp.</ENAMEX>, an analytical-instruments maker, and may seek control of the company.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crane</ENAMEX>, a maker of engineered products for aerospace, construction, defense and other uses, made the disclosure in a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> filing.
In the filing, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Crane</ENAMEX> said that in the past it considered seeking control of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milton Roy</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Petersburg</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fla.</ENAMEX>, through a merger or tender offer and that it expects to continue to evaluate an acquisition from time to time. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Crane</ENAMEX> officials didn't return phone calls seeking comment.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John M. Mcnamara</ENAMEX>, chief financial officer of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milton Roy</ENAMEX>, said the company has no comment on <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Crane</ENAMEX>'s filing.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milton Roy</ENAMEX> recently fended off unsolicited overtures from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thermo Electron Corp.</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Waltham</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, maker of biomedical products. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milton Roy</ENAMEX> disclosed in May that it was approached for a possible acquisition by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thermo Electron</ENAMEX>, which agreed to purchase <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milton Roy</ENAMEX>'s liquid-chromatography line for $22 million in February. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thermo Electron</ENAMEX> acquired some 6% of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milton Roy</ENAMEX>'s common stock before throwing in the towel and reducing its stake in early September.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Gabelli Group</ENAMEX> began raising its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Milton Roy</ENAMEX> stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">July</ENAMEX>, and holds 14.6%, according to a recent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> filing. It hasn't made merger overtures to the board.
Earlier this month, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Milton Roy</ENAMEX> signed a letter of intent to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Automated Custom Systems Inc.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Orange</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, and its sister operation, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Environmental Testing Co.</ENAMEX>, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Aurora</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colo</ENAMEX>. The companies are automotive-emissions-testing concerns.
