Pilots of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Express Corp.</ENAMEX> voted to reject affiliation with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Line Pilots Association</ENAMEX>, giving a resounding victory to the company's founder and chairman, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Frederick W. Smith</ENAMEX>.
In the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Mediation Board</ENAMEX> election, 709 pilots voted to support the union, out of a total electorate of 2,022 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Express</ENAMEX> aviators. The results were unexpectedly dismal for the pro-union side, especially given that some 960 eligible voters were former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger International Inc.</ENAMEX> pilots who had been longtime <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ALPA</ENAMEX> members. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Express</ENAMEX> bought Tiger in February for $880 million.
``We're stunned,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barney Barnhardt</ENAMEX>, a captain and leader of the pro-ALPA campaign. ``Apparently, we lost a lot of the Tiger votes. I don't know why.''
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX> had campaigned hard against the union, insisting in company materials that a union would infuse unnecessary confict into the company's employee relations. A pilots' union would have been <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Express</ENAMEX>'s first major collective bargaining unit in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, and company executives had feared that it would soften <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal's</ENAMEX> gung-ho, customer-driven culture.
``The company feels very gratified'' with the vote, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">T. Allan Mcartor</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal's</ENAMEX> senior vice president, air operations. ``We like to think that the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Express</ENAMEX> management can deal directly with its pilots without a union's intervention.'' Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Smith</ENAMEX>, through a spokesman, declined to be interviewed yesterday.
In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ALPA</ENAMEX> issued a statement saying the union was ``disappointed'' with the election's outcome. It said it filed an objection with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Mediation Board</ENAMEX>, protesting ``improprieties'' in the vote. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Specifically</ENAMEX>, the union is contending, among other charges, that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Express</ENAMEX> misled pilots by calling the Flight Crewmembers <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Handbook</ENAMEX> a valid contract.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barnhardt</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX> was apparently successful in its effort to persuade former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger</ENAMEX> pilots to give the company a chance without a union. The company had told pilots that it's much easier to vote in a union than to vote one out. ``It looks like the `let's-give-it-a-year campaign' worked,'' said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barnhardt</ENAMEX>.
As for the veteran <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX> pilots, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barnhardt</ENAMEX> said the pro-union side had counted on getting at least 100 of them to support <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">ALPA</ENAMEX>. But it seems many fewer than that actually voted for the union, probably because of fears that union rules would hurt them in their battle over seniority issues against the former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger</ENAMEX> pilots.
Depending on how a mediator reconciles the different job classifications of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Express</ENAMEX> still faces possible union elections this fall among airplane mechanics, ramp workers and stock clerks.
