<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival Cruise Lines Inc.</ENAMEX>'s common stock was dragged down yesterday amid concerns that a bankruptcy filing by a Finnish shipbuilder would delay delivery of three big cruise ships.
``There is just a tremendous amount of uncertainty about what the effect, if any, of all this is,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John P. Uphoff</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Raymond James Associates Inc.</ENAMEX> ``I didn't even know that a company in a socialistic country could file for bankruptcy.''
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival</ENAMEX> said the ``Fantasy,'' the first of the three $200 million ships that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival</ENAMEX> has on order, is scheduled to be delivered next month, just in time for the winter tourist season in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Caribbean</ENAMEX>. That ship, which would carry about 2,050 passengers, would expand the capacity of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival</ENAMEX>'s existing 14-ship fleet by 24%. The second ship, which is half-completed, is scheduled to be delivered in fall 1990, and the third in fall 1991.
Analysts weren't willing to speculate on how much money <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival</ENAMEX> might lose through deposits. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Normally</ENAMEX>, a company pays a portion of the total cost of a ship as it reaches various stages of construction. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival</ENAMEX>, for example, has already paid about $160 million of the total cost for Fantasy. Some analysts say this may give it the right to seize the ship if the situation warrants it.
According to reports from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Finland</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Waertsilae Marine</ENAMEX>, 19%-owned by conglomerate <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oy Waertsilae</ENAMEX>, filed for bankruptcy yesterday after the shipyard's contractors had started to demand bank guarantees. The shipyard disclosed in mid-August that it expected losses stemming from a series of unprofitable orders.
