<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> financier <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Saul Steinberg</ENAMEX> sought federal permission to buy more than 15% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX>' parent, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL Corp.</ENAMEX>, saying he might seek control of the nation's second-largest airline.
Although takeover experts said they doubted Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX> will make a bid by himself, the application by his <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance Group Holdings Inc.</ENAMEX> could signal his interest in helping revive a failed labor-management bid.
Such an application for federal antitrust clearance is necessary for any investor that might seek control. But some investors have used such filings to boost the value of their stock holdings, which -- without buying more stock -- they then sold.
Takeover stock traders were puzzled by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance</ENAMEX> filing and cautioned that it doesn't mean Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX> will definitely seek control. ``Maybe he just wants to make something happen,'' said one takeover expert.
One investment banker said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX> may be trying to position himself as a friendly investor who could help <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stephen Wolf</ENAMEX> revive a failed labor-management bid. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX>, he suggested, could replace <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">British Airways PLC</ENAMEX>, which has withdrawn from the buy-out group.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance</ENAMEX> had already bought and sold <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock at a big profit without making an antitrust filing before the collapse Oct. 13 of the $6.79 billion, $300-a-share labor-management buy-out. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance</ENAMEX> acquired a 7% <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stake early this year at an average cost of $110 a share, and reduced its stake to 4.7% after <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> accepted the bid at prices higher than $282 a share.
Market sources said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance</ENAMEX> has already sold its entire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stake, and thus wouldn't have any reason to file the application simply to boost the value of its stock. But the exact amount of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance</ENAMEX>'s current holding hasn't been formally disclosed.
The filing adds a new twist to market speculation that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston Partners</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> money manager, has bought more than 5% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> stock and may challenge the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> board's decision last week to remain independent. Speculation about <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coniston</ENAMEX> has caused the stock to rebound from a low of $145.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s announcement came after the market closed yesterday. In composite <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> trading, the shares closed at $177, up $1.50. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> wouldn't elaborate on a statement that it had been notified of the filing by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance</ENAMEX> confirmed the filing but wouldn't elaborate.
Some takeover experts were skeptical, saying it was possible that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX> made the filing only to help boost the value of any remaining <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reliance</ENAMEX> stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steinberg</ENAMEX> is thought to be on friendly terms with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX>'s Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wolf</ENAMEX>. The investor was instrumental in tapping Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wolf</ENAMEX> to run the air cargo unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tiger International Inc.</ENAMEX> Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wolf</ENAMEX>'s success in that job helped him land the top job with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">UAL</ENAMEX> in December 1987.
But any potential acquirer must attempt to reach some kind of accord with the company's employees, primarily its pilots and the powerful machinists' union, which has opposed a takeover.
