<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amoco Corp.</ENAMEX> said third-quarter net income plunged 39% to $336 million, or 65 cents a share, as gasoline refining and marketing profits lagged substantially behind last year's record level.
A charge of $80 million related to projected environmental costs in its refining and marketing operations further depressed results. A spokesman said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amoco</ENAMEX> completed an environmental analysis last quarter but that no single clean-up project was responsible.
In the 1988 third quarter, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX>-based oil company earned $552 million, or $1.07 a share. Revenue in the latest quarter rose 12% to $6.6 billion from $5.91 billion. Aside from the special charge, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amoco</ENAMEX>'s results were in line with Wall Street estimates. The company's stock ended at $48.375, up 25 cents in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amoco</ENAMEX>'s refining and marketing profit in the quarter fell to $134 million from $319 million. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Chemical</ENAMEX> earnings declined by one-third to $120 million last year's robust levels.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amoco</ENAMEX>'s domestic oil and natural gas operations recorded a profit of $104 million in the quarter compared with a loss of $5 million, ``primarily on the strength of higher crude oil prices,'' said Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard M. Morrow</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amoco</ENAMEX> also sharply boosted natural-gas output, part of it from properties acquired from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tenneco Inc.</ENAMEX> last year.
But foreign exploration and production earnings fell sharply, to $12 million from $95 million. Higher oil prices weren't enough to offset a roughly $20 million charge related to a 10% reduction in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amoco</ENAMEX>'s Canadian work force as well as increased exploration expenses.
For the nine months, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Amoco</ENAMEX> said that net income fell to $1.29 billion from $1.69 billion but if unusual items are excluded, operations produced essentially flat results. Revenue rose 12% to $19.93 billion from $17.73 billion.
