<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodyear Tire & Rubber Co.</ENAMEX>, buoyed by improved operating profit in its tire segment, reported that third-quarter net income rose 11% to $70.5 million, or $1.22 a share.
In the year-ago period, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodyear</ENAMEX> had net of $63.5 million, or $1.11 a share.
Sales rose slightly to $2.68 billion, from $2.66 billion.
However, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Harry Millis</ENAMEX>, an analyst at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Mcdonald & Co.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cleveland</ENAMEX>, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodyear</ENAMEX>'s results ``fell at the bottom'' of his range of estimates. Excluding an increase in the tax rate and the effects of foreign currency translations, Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Millis</ENAMEX> said the company's results ``were still a little disappointing.''
The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Akron</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ohio</ENAMEX>-based company said pretax operating income in its tire segment jumped about 31% to $196.2 million from $150.2 million a year earlier, reflecting improvements in raw material costs, sales of replacement tires and pricing.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mcdonald</ENAMEX>'s Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Millis</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodyear</ENAMEX> appeared to have held or gained some market share in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> for the first time since the second quarter of 1988.
But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodyear</ENAMEX> said total U.S. tire unit sales were off about 2%. Total tire segment sales were up only about 1% to $2.2 billion, and the company said it reduced manufacturing levels at some of its U.S. tire plants because of inventory adjustments and slackened production by auto makers.
In the latest quarter, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Goodyear</ENAMEX>'s tax rate was 51% compared with 41% a year earlier. As a result, total tax outlays were $73.5 million, compared with $44.1 million the year earlier.
For the nine months, profit skidded about 35%, reflecting charges taken in this year's second quarter and the effect of translations of weaker foreign currencies into the stronger U.S. dollar.
Net was $192.1 million, or $3.33 a share, compared with net of $293.7 million, or $5.13 a share, the year earlier.
The latest nine months included charges of $95 million related to the company's South African subsidiary and unused pipe sold by its crude oil pipeline unit.
Sales rose nearly 2% to $8.13 billion from $7.98 billion.
