<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kennametal</ENAMEX> is a carbide-products and cutting-tools company. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">J&L</ENAMEX>, whose principal offices are in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Detroit</ENAMEX>, is a mail-order distributer of industrial tools and supplies.
The acquisition is subject to approval by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kennametal</ENAMEX>'s board.
