<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hudson's Bay Co.</ENAMEX> announced terms of a previously proposed rights issue that is expected to raise about 396 million Canadian dollars (US$337 million) net of expenses.
Proceeds of the offering will be used to redeem C$264 million of preferred shares and to reduce short-term debt, the company said.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hudson's Bay</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Woodbridge Co.</ENAMEX>, which currently holds about 77% of the ordinary shares, will subscribe for all the shares to which it is entitled and for any shares that aren't otherwise taken up. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Woodbridge</ENAMEX> is a holding company owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Toronto</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomson</ENAMEX> family.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hudson's Bay</ENAMEX> said it will redeem 9.5 million Series H preferred shares on Oct. 31 at a price of C$27.75 each. The move was approved at a special shareholders' meeting yesterday.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gary Lukassen</ENAMEX>, chief financial officer, said redemption of the preferred shares, originally issued at C$25 each, will eliminate dividend payments of C$17.9 million annually.
