The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Office of Thrift Supervision</ENAMEX> banned <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">B.J. Garman</ENAMEX>, a former director of the failed <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vision Banc Savings Association</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Kingsville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas</ENAMEX>, from working in any financial institution insured by the government.
The office, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury Department</ENAMEX> unit that is the successor to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Home Loan Bank Board</ENAMEX>, said this was the first announcement of an enforcement action since this year's thrift-bailout legislation ordered that all such actions by federal banking regulators be made public.
Generally, regulators haven't announced enforcement actions in the past. Indeed, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">OTS</ENAMEX> said that before the law took effect Aug. 9, it banned another ``key <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Vision Banc</ENAMEX> insider'' from insured financial institutions. That individual wasn't identified.
Ms. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Garman</ENAMEX> couldn't be reached for comment.
