The ruling follows a host of problems at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tucson Electric</ENAMEX>, including major write-downs, a 60% slash in the common stock dividend and the departure of former Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Einar Greve</ENAMEX> during a company investigation of his stock sales.
The decision was announced after trading ended. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tucson Electric</ENAMEX> closed at $20.875 a share, down 25 cents, in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> composite trading.
A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Tucson Electric</ENAMEX> spokesman said the utility was disappointed by the commission's decision and ``concerned about the financial integrity of the company.
