``Please submit                                                  your offers,'' says <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Felipe Bince Jr</ENAMEX>.
Indeed. Recently, the trust failed to auction off the paper mill, a bank, an office building and a small cotton-ginning plant. Of the four, only the bank and the plant drew bids -- one apiece.
In October 1987, President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Corazon Aquino</ENAMEX> vowed that her government would ``get out of business'' by selling all or part of the state's holdings in the many companies taken over by the government during the 20-year rule of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ferdinand Marcos</ENAMEX>. Two years later, Mrs. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Aquino</ENAMEX>'s promise remains largely unfulfilled.
October is a critical month for the privatization program. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manila</ENAMEX> is offering several major assets for the first time and is trying to conclude sales already arranged. In addition, the government is scheduled to unveil plans for privatizing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philippine Airlines</ENAMEX>, the national carrier, an effort that lawyer and business columnist <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rodolfo Romero</ENAMEX> calls ``the bellwether of privatization.'' All told, there are assets on the line valued at up to $1.03 billion.
To be sure, the program hasn't completely stalled. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asset Privatization Trust</ENAMEX>, the agency chiefly responsible for selling government-held properties, has recorded sales of more than $500 million since it began functioning in December 1986. But its success has been largely in the sale of small, nonperforming companies, which are valued for their assets.
Dealing with the sales this month could be particularly challenging because almost every problem that has hobbled the program in the past is popping up again. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ramon Garcia</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asset Trust</ENAMEX>'s executive trustee, admits to what he calls ``temporary setbacks.'' In light of the poor results recently, he says, the agency is adopting an ``attitude of flexibility.''
October's troubles began when the trust failed to sell a state-owned commercial bank, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Associated Bank</ENAMEX>, for the minimum price of 671 million pesos ($31 million). At the end of the month, the agency again will offer the bank. But instead of a minimum price, only a target price will be established.
Bankers say, however, that the government may have difficulty selling the institution even without a floor price. The bank has a negative net worth, they say.
In addition, special bidding rules give the bank's former owner, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leonardo Ty</ENAMEX>, the right to match the highest bid. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ty</ENAMEX> lost control to the government in 1980 when a government bank made emergency loans to the cash-strapped institution. In 1983, the loans were converted into equity, giving <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manila</ENAMEX> 98% of the bank, but with the understanding that Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ty</ENAMEX> had repurchase rights. His ability to match any bid has scared off many potential buyers.
But according to bankers and stock analysts who have studied the paper mill, price isn't the only consideration. As it stands now, the government would continue to hold 45% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Picop</ENAMEX> after the 36% stake is sold. (About 7.5% of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Picop</ENAMEX> is publicly traded and other shareholders own the rest of the equity.) Potential buyers, mostly foreign companies, are reluctant to take a non-controlling stake in a company that, by the government's own reckoning, needs some $100 million in new capital for rehabilitation.
The prospect of buying into a cash-hungry company without getting management control persuaded at least three foreign buyers, including a member of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Elders group</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX>, to pull out of the bidding, the bankers and analysts say.
Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Garcia</ENAMEX> acknowledges the problem and says the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asset Trust</ENAMEX> will study why the bidding failed and what changes the agency may be able to offer. Under government regulations, however, foreign ownership of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Picop</ENAMEX>'s equity is limited to 40%.
Even though the government would retain the 45% stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Picop</ENAMEX>, critics have accused the trust of selling out to foreigners. A series of newspaper articles accused the trust of short-changing the government over the Picop sale. Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Garcia</ENAMEX> says he has been notified of congressional hearings on the Picop bidding and possible legislation covering the paper mill's sale, both prompted by the criticism of the agency.
The question of control could further hinder long-delayed plans for the government to divest itself of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philippine Airlines</ENAMEX>, in which it has a 99% stake. The carrier has valuable trans-Pacific and Asian routes but it remains debt-laden and poorly managed.
