<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada Inc.</ENAMEX> revised the terms of its restructuring and extended to Feb. 28, 1990, the deadline to complete the sale of its hotel business to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New World Development Co.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Prime Motor Inns Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fairfield</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada</ENAMEX>'s previous plan was derailed by upheaval in the junk-bond market that hindered the offering of $400 million in high-yield securities of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Aztar Corp.</ENAMEX>, the new company that will operate <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada</ENAMEX>'s casinos in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nevada</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic City</ENAMEX>,
Under the new terms, New World will still pay $540 million for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada</ENAMEX>'s hotel business, subject to adjustment at closing, but <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada</ENAMEX> will now reimburse <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New World</ENAMEX> for $10 million in expenses. Prime will still manage <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada</ENAMEX>'s domestic franchise system when the sale closes.
Revised terms call for each <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada</ENAMEX> common share to be exchanged for $1 in cash, subject to possible reduction, and one share of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Aztar</ENAMEX> common stock. Shareholders will also receive one cent per share for the redemption of preferred stock purchase rights.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada's</ENAMEX> stock rose 87.5 cents on the news to close at $11.25 in composite <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> trading. The announcement dispelled some Wall Street observers' fears that New World might demand a huge premium for the delay, or scrap the deal entirely. The previous deadline to complete the sale was Nov. 30.
The much-revised restructuring, which was first announced in October 1988, must again be approved by shareholders and state casino regulators in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nevada</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Jersey</ENAMEX>. Financing plans include raising $170 million in debt secured by the company's holdings in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Jersey</ENAMEX>.
In May, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ramada</ENAMEX> sold its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marie Callender Pie Shops Inc.</ENAMEX> unit to a group of private investors as part of its plan to focus on its casinos in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic City</ENAMEX> and in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Las Vegas</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Laughlin</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nev</ENAMEX>.
