<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Federal Bancorp Inc.</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Clarkson</ENAMEX>, its chairman, president and chief executive officer, retired effective yesterday. The company also said its board recently instituted a review of internal policies and procedures, including activities conducted by Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Clarkson</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Federal</ENAMEX> said Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Clarkson</ENAMEX>, 65 years old, is ``fully cooperating in the continuing review.''
``None of the activities being reviewed has any adverse effect on the financial condition of the bank or its depositors,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Federal Savings Bank & Trust</ENAMEX>'s president, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leo D. Ottoni</ENAMEX>, said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Federal Savings</ENAMEX> is a subsidiary of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Federal Bancorp</ENAMEX>.
The company declined to disclose further details, but said that the inquiry is continuing and that it wasn't forced by banking regulators. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Federal</ENAMEX> said no further announcements are expected before the review is finished.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Federal</ENAMEX> named Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ottoni</ENAMEX> president and chief executive to succeed Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Clarkson</ENAMEX> and elected him as a director. The post of chairman will remain vacant indefinitely, a company spokesman said. Earlier this month Mr. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ottoni</ENAMEX>, 64, was named acting president and chief executive of the holding company and the savings bank unit. Previously he had been senior vice president in charge of the savings bank's trust division.
