<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ardent Computer Corp.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stellar Computer Inc.</ENAMEX> said they completed the merger that the closely held companies announced Aug. 30.
The new company, called <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stardent Computer Inc.</ENAMEX>, also said it named <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John William Poduska</ENAMEX>, former chairman and chief executive of Stellar, to the posts of president and chief executive.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Allen H. Michels</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ardent</ENAMEX>'s former president and chief executive, was named chairman of the new company. The two men had been serving as co-chairmen and co-chief executive officers.
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stardent</ENAMEX> said it would combine its two product lines -- both high-performance graphics computers -- by the 1991 first quarter. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Stardent</ENAMEX> will be based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Newton</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, but will maintain its operations in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sunnyvale</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>
