A shareholder filed suit, seeking to block <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Unitel Video Inc.</ENAMEX>'s proposed plan to be acquired by a new affiliate of closely held <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Kenmare Capital Corp.</ENAMEX> for $15 a share, or $33.6 million.
The suit, which seeks class-action status, was filed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Delaware</ENAMEX> Chancery Court. The complaint alleges that the price is ``unfair and grossly inadequate'' and that the defendants are seeking to ensure a ``lockup'' of the purchase of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Unitel</ENAMEX>, thereby discouraging other bids. It seeks unspecified money damages. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> company called the lawsuit without merit.
Shareholders are scheduled to vote on the transaction Nov.
